<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-13T11:50:34+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Computer Help Northern Ireland</title><subtitle>Professional mobile computer support in County Down</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Tips for byuying a new laptop</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2021/02/18/tips-for-buying-a-new-laptop.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tips for byuying a new laptop" /><published>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2021/02/18/tips-for-buying-a-new-laptop</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2021/02/18/tips-for-buying-a-new-laptop.html">&lt;p&gt;People often ask for advice about which laptop is best. There is no easy answer to this question, but I can help to narrow down the choices based on a few factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All computers have a few things in common, so we can use these components when comparison shopping. The main components affecting a computer’s performance are its CPU (a.k.a. processor), its internal storage device (a hard drive or solid-state drive [SSD]), the amount of memory (a.k.a. RAM), and the size and type of screen. Let’s look at each of these components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cpu--processor&quot;&gt;CPU / processor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly every laptop sold today has a CPU made by either Intel or AMD. Intel CPUs are usually called a ‘Core-i &lt;em&gt;Something&lt;/em&gt;’, such as a Core-i3, i5, i7, or i9, and AMD CPUs have names like Athlon or Ryzen 3, 5, or 9. CPU speeds vary considerably, but one of the most significant differences among CPUs is ‘cores’ and ‘thread’ count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today’s consumer-grade CPUs have anywhere from two to 16 cores and can work on between two and 32 threads at any given time. When comparing cores and threads, more is better. That is, a CPU that contains four cores and can process eight threads (sometimes shown as ‘Cores/Threads: 4/8’) is better than a Core/Thread value of 2/4 or even 4/4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb:&lt;/strong&gt; core/thread count of at &lt;em&gt;least&lt;/em&gt; 4/4; 4/8 will be noticibly faster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ssd--storage--drive&quot;&gt;SSD / storage / drive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, you should not buy a laptop that has a mechanical hard drive inside. Mechanical drives are much slower and more fragile than the newer solid-state drives (SSDs) that are becoming commonplace. Almost all new laptops ship with SSDs, but you need to ensure that the SSD is large enough for your requirements. Choosing a lower-cost, smaller SSD (e.g. anything less than 250 GB) can lead to issues in the future when the drive becomes full. This is especially true in some of the very low-cost laptops that ship with 32 GB SSDs–these fill up quickly, preventing Windows Update from functioning at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb:&lt;/strong&gt; only SSD, at least 256 GB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ram--memory&quot;&gt;RAM / memory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of memory (a.k.a. RAM) inside a computer dictates how much you can do at any given time. The analaogy to humans is that RAM is like short-term memory. Each running appliation and open file uses some of the RAM in a PC, and when that RAM becomes full, Windows has to ‘swap’ some of the data out of RAM and onto your internal storage (hopefully a SSD)–a process that takes time and makes your computer feel slower than it should. Becuase of this, more RAM is always better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb:&lt;/strong&gt; at least 4GB, 8GB is best&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;screen&quot;&gt;Screen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of a laptop’s screen has a huge impact on the overall size of the laptop, so it often makes sense to start your search by deciding how big you want the screen to be. Many laptops are also available with touch screens and/or ‘convertible’ screens (e.g. where the screen folds all the way back, making it look like a tablet PC). If you know what size screen and whether yo need a touch screen, you can use those factors to significantly filter your laptop search results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rule of thumb:&lt;/strong&gt; start your search by deciding whether you need a touch screen&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">People often ask for advice about which laptop is best. There is no easy answer to this question, but I can help to narrow down the choices based on a few factors.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New office in Newcastle</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/homepage/office/2020/10/07/new-office-in-newcastle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New office in Newcastle" /><published>2020-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/homepage/office/2020/10/07/new-office-in-newcastle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/homepage/office/2020/10/07/new-office-in-newcastle.html">&lt;p&gt;After working from our home for over 18 months, last week we officially opened our new office space at &lt;a href=&quot;https://g.page/computer-help-ni?share&quot;&gt;6 Downs Road in Newcastle&lt;/a&gt;. Being in the town and close to the sea is lovely, and we hope our location will make it more convenient for customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- The grid: four columns --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/office01.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Exterior&quot; onclick=&quot;showPhoto(this);&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/office02.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Reception&quot; onclick=&quot;showPhoto(this);&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/office03.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Waiting area&quot; onclick=&quot;showPhoto(this);&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/office04.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Main office&quot; onclick=&quot;showPhoto(this);&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!-- The expanding image container --&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;!-- Close the image --&gt;
  &lt;span onclick=&quot;this.parentElement.style.display='none'&quot; class=&quot;closebtn&quot;&gt;&amp;times;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;!-- Expanded image --&gt;
  &lt;img id=&quot;expandedImg&quot; style=&quot;width:100%&quot; alt=&quot;Exterior&quot; src=&quot;/assets/images/office01.JPG&quot; /&gt;

  &lt;!-- Image text --&gt;
  &lt;div id=&quot;imgtext&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we're settled in and ready for business, stop in or give us a call to discuss your computer issues; we're always happy to help.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">After working from our home for over 18 months, last week we officially opened our new office space at 6 Downs Road in Newcastle. Being in the town and close to the sea is lovely, and we hope our location will make it more convenient for customers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AbilityNet offers free technology support</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2020/03/01/abilitynet-offers-free-technology-support.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AbilityNet offers free technology support" /><published>2020-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2020/03/01/abilitynet-offers-free-technology-support</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/support/2020/03/01/abilitynet-offers-free-technology-support.html">&lt;p&gt;As a registered charity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abilitynet.org.uk/&quot;&gt;AbilityNet&lt;/a&gt; exists to change the lives of older people and people with a disability by helping them to use digital technology. They are supported by IBM and Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ImageRight&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/pdf/FS-A5_flyer_wheelchair.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/AbilityNet-flyer-small.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;AbilityNet flyer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The free helpline 0800 269 545 is available for advice and information. They also have a nationwide network of 280 carefully selected and vetted AbilityNet ITCanHelp volunteers (including myself) who can visit clients in their own homes and support them with their technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as diagnosing and fixing most computer related problems, their ITCanHelp volunteers can help with sending and receiving emails, using the internet, installing new hardware and software, and giving impartial advice on IT equipment and software.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is something that you or anyone you come into contact with might benefit from, they would welcome hearing from you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you would like to chat further about their service, call them on 0800 269 545 or email &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:enquiries@abilitynet.org.uk&quot;&gt;enquiries@abilitynet.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;. For more information visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.abilitynet.org.uk/at-home&quot;&gt;https://www.abilitynet.org.uk/at-home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">As a registered charity AbilityNet exists to change the lives of older people and people with a disability by helping them to use digital technology. They are supported by IBM and Microsoft.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Upgrade your old computer to Windows 10</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/2019/11/20/upgrade-to-Windows-10.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Upgrade your old computer to Windows 10" /><published>2019-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/2019/11/20/upgrade-to-Windows-10</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/2019/11/20/upgrade-to-Windows-10.html">&lt;p&gt;Microsoft Windows 10 runs well on most PCs or laptops built during the past 10 years—usually &lt;em&gt;much better&lt;/em&gt; than Windows 7 or 8/8.1 does. It also has excellent security features built-in, making it possible to ditch those third-party antivirus packages while still protecting your computer from infections. With a solid-state drive and at least 2GB of RAM, most any computer will run well on Windows 10. (For details about solid-state drives, see our blog post &lt;a href=&quot;/performance/upgrade/ssd/2019/08/10/dont-replace-your-old-computer-upgrade-it.html&quot;&gt;Don’t replace your old computer, upgrade it!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ImageRight&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/Windows10-laptop_full.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/Windows10-laptop_thumb.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;Old laptop running Windows 10&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to better performance, another good reason to upgrade to Windows 10 is that Microsoft is ending support for its older operating systems. They no longer support Windows XP at all, meaning any new security issues found in XP will not be patched. Windows 7 is approaching the end of its ‘extended support’ phase as well, so it will no longer receive security updates after 14 January, 2020. For details of how Microsoft supports its older operating systems, see this article by Chris Hoffman: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.howtogeek.com/308290/how-long-will-microsoft-support-my-version-of-windows-with-security-updates/&quot;&gt;How Long Will Microsoft Support My Version of Windows with Security Updates?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your computer is still running on an older version of Windows, give us a call today to find out if it can be upgraded. We’ll give you a no-obligation quote and answer any questions you have about the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">Microsoft Windows 10 runs well on most PCs or laptops built during the past 10 years—usually much better than Windows 7 or 8/8.1 does. It also has excellent security features built-in, making it possible to ditch those third-party antivirus packages while still protecting your computer from infections. With a solid-state drive and at least 2GB of RAM, most any computer will run well on Windows 10. (For details about solid-state drives, see our blog post Don’t replace your old computer, upgrade it!)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keep your online profile secure</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/10/04/keep-your-online-profile-secure.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keep your online profile secure" /><published>2019-10-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/10/04/keep-your-online-profile-secure</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/10/04/keep-your-online-profile-secure.html">&lt;p&gt;If you’ve used the Internet for long, your personal information—name, email address, possibly your password—has probably been included in at least one data breach. If so, the email address and password exposed in the breach are no longer safe to use &lt;em&gt;anywhere&lt;/em&gt;. Trust me, I learned this the hard way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ImageRight&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/password.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;Security&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Like many people, I used to use the same two or three passwords for years: one for most websites, a stronger one for ‘important’ sites, and my ever-changing work password at my job. I knew that I should have been using a unique password at every site, but changing my hundreds of website passwords just seemed too difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one day I received a message from Tesco, confirming a purchase that I hadn’t made. Tesco Customer Service confirmed that someone had accessed my account using the same password that was exposed in the LinkedIn data breach, more than a year earlier. The thief logged into my account, changed the address and password, and spent £38 in Tesco vouchers—all because I had reused my password!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now use a unique, strong password at each site where I have an account. I could never remember all of these passwords, so I use a password manager to keep track of them all. There are many such tool available today: LastPass, 1Password, Keeper, True Key, etc. If you’d like help choosing a password manager or have any other security questions or concerns, I’d love to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Protecting passwords—a checklist:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a unique password for each website or account.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use strong passwords: include a mix of upper-and lower-case letters, numbers, and special characters, or use a longer ‘pass phrase.’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep your passwords confidential.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use a password manager to make it easy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">If you’ve used the Internet for long, your personal information—name, email address, possibly your password—has probably been included in at least one data breach. If so, the email address and password exposed in the breach are no longer safe to use anywhere. Trust me, I learned this the hard way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Don’t replace your old computer, upgrade it!</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/ssd/2019/08/10/dont-replace-your-old-computer-upgrade-it.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Don't replace your old computer, upgrade it!" /><published>2019-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/ssd/2019/08/10/dont-replace-your-old-computer-upgrade-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/performance/upgrade/ssd/2019/08/10/dont-replace-your-old-computer-upgrade-it.html">&lt;p&gt;A slow computer is usually caused by a slow hard drive. From £105, a Windows PC with a 500GB drive can be updated to run significantly faster by upgrading to a solid-state drive (SSD).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, nearly every computer was built using a standard hard drive which uses magnetic heads to read and write data on spinning metal platters. Such hard drives can read data at a maximum rate of 120 megabytes per second (MB/s) under ideal conditions, and that rate is usually much slower under normal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;ImageRight&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/images/ssd-hdd_full.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ssd-hdd_thumb.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;Internal view of SSD and HDD&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solid-state drive has no moving parts; it’s essentially a large amount of special computer memory that remembers its contents even when the computer is turned off. These drives are very fast, achieving data read rates of around 500 MB/s—four or five times faster than standard hard drives— under normal conditions.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=D6ZxxWtILfw&quot;&gt;Watch our YouTube video comparing the performance of an SSD to that of a standard hard drive.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, we can upgrade a computer to an SSD in less than two hours. To see if your PC can be upgraded, call or email Computer Help Northern Ireland. We’ll be happy to discuss your options and provide a quote free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">A slow computer is usually caused by a slow hard drive. From £105, a Windows PC with a 500GB drive can be updated to run significantly faster by upgrading to a solid-state drive (SSD).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How attackers use Microsoft Office</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/06/23/how-attackers-use-microsoft-office.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How attackers use Microsoft Office" /><published>2019-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-06-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/06/23/how-attackers-use-microsoft-office</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/06/23/how-attackers-use-microsoft-office.html">&lt;p&gt;Protecting a Microsoft Word, Excel, or other Office file with a password encrypts the contents of the file. This prevents opening the file without the password or viewing its contents directly. It also prevents security tools from scanning the file for viruses or malicious code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attackers take advantage of this by sending password-protected documents to sneak malware past our email security software. If you receive a password-protected file that you were not expecting, proceed with caution! Assume the file could contain malware, and ask for help if you’re not sure how to stay safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Macros allow you to run scripts or code within a Microsoft Office document. Sometimes this code is expected and required for a document or spreadsheet to display correctly, but other times this code is malicious and will attempt to install a virus or malicious software on your computer. If a document contains a macro, you will see a security warning and ‘Enable Content’ button:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ImageCenter&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog-ms-office-security-warning.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;Microsoft Office security warning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking the button allows the embedded code to run, so only click if you know the document is safe and that macros are expected and required. If you have any doubt, contact the person who sent the document or phone Computer Help NI for advice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">Protecting a Microsoft Word, Excel, or other Office file with a password encrypts the contents of the file. This prevents opening the file without the password or viewing its contents directly. It also prevents security tools from scanning the file for viruses or malicious code.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The padlock doesn’t mean a site is safe</title><link href="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/04/07/the-padlock-doesnt-mean-its-safe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The padlock doesn't mean a site is safe" /><published>2019-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2019-04-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/04/07/the-padlock-doesnt-mean-its-safe</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://0.0.0.0:4000/security/2019/04/07/the-padlock-doesnt-mean-its-safe.html">&lt;p&gt;Most web browsers show a padlock in the address bar when you’re securely connected to a website. This means the information sent between your browser and the web server is encrypted, so eavesdroppers are unable to read passwords, payment details, or any other sensitive information that might be sent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the padlock indicates a secure &lt;em&gt;connection&lt;/em&gt;, it does not guarantee the website itself is &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt;. Some phishing attacks include links to fake websites that use secure connections, and when visiting such a website your browser would show a padlock to indicate a secure connection &lt;em&gt;even when connected to a fake website&lt;/em&gt;. For example, this forged PayPal site uses a secure connection:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;ImageCenter&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/blog-fake-paypal-login.png&quot; alt=&quot;Alt&quot; title=&quot;Forged PayPal site&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When accessing a secure website, look carefully at the web address. Sometimes the address is too long for your browser so display, so part of it may be hidden by the address bar. In such cases, an address that looks like ‘www.paypal.com’ might actually be ‘www.paypal.com-e.site’ or something similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before sending sensitive information to a website, ensure the web address is correct by clicking on the address and reading what’s there. Everything in between ‘https://’ and the next slash ‘/’ should match what you would expect. In our PayPal example, you should see something like ‘www.paypal.com’ or ‘paypal.co.uk’, not ‘www.paypal.com-e.site’. If in doubt, phone Computer Help NI for advice.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Dave Rand</name></author><summary type="html">Most web browsers show a padlock in the address bar when you’re securely connected to a website. This means the information sent between your browser and the web server is encrypted, so eavesdroppers are unable to read passwords, payment details, or any other sensitive information that might be sent.</summary></entry></feed>